Never forget why you are the church.
Romans chapter 12, we're talking about or
we're looking at what God expects of us in our relationships
with others.
We've looking at the impact of the gospel, regarding our relationships.
We have gone over quite a lot already, the past several weeks.
So we're going to look at the text in review here.
Romans chapter 12, verse 9 through 12 says this.
Let love be without the simulation.
That means without hypocrisy.
Abhor that which is evil, clea to that, which is good.
Be kindly affection, one to another, would brotherly love and
honor preferring one another.
Not slothful in business, fervent in spirit,
serving the Lord.
Rejoicing in hope.
Patient and tribulation, continuing instant in prayer.
You know, it's amazing to me how as you grow in God's
word, God gives you opportunities to share his
word in ways that you never would think or imagine.
And I was at the gym yesterday and I was
working out, but also on the phone with our director of mission,
Scott Brown, just getting some advice and counsel.
I wear him out all the time, asking questions, and so I was doing that.
And then a young man came up to me and he said, are you on the phone?
And I'm like, well, I'm not talking to myself like this.
But yes, I'm on the phone.
And I said, what's up, man?
And I've known him since he was like that big.
he said, I just got some questions.
And I said, okay, well, let me get off this phone.
And don't go nowhere.
We'll talk.
And so I got off the phone, went and found.
I said, okay, what would you like to talk about?
And man, he just starts sharing with me.
He basically just throws up on me all the things that God
has shown him and how he feels like he's more sober-minded
and he's gotten into fasting intentionally for the Lord and
how that has really just opened his eyes to the things that
he's been partaking in that he shouldn't be partaking in.
And he's just telling me, he said, he said, Pastor Jacob,
he said, I feel like the last 2 weeks I've seen things so
much differently and I go to the places that I used to
go to and it's not fun anymore.
It's not, I don't feel welcomed anymore.
And I was able to share with him Romans, chapter 12,
where it says this, listen, man, abhor that, which is evil.
Cling to that, which is good.
And sometimes the simplest advice is
the best possible advice.
Amen?
I said, listen, you're at this time now.
You said 2 weeks, you've not been doing this, you've not been doing that, and you've really been focusing.
said, listen, hey, that 2 weeks is very important.
But the enemy knows exactly how excited you are right now.
And sometimes if we're not careful, when we're on no
spiritual highs, the moment we drop down and we fall,
it's worse than even before, if we don't respond properly.
So I said, listen, as you're growing strength, you need to distance yourself
from those things and people that you once hung out with
and did stuff with.
Does that make sense?
Listen, that's not just for a 21 year old young man.
That's for all of us.
Romans 12 was written for all of us.
Abhor.
That is to distance ourselves from what is evil and
to cling to that which is good.
So this morning we move on to the next command found in Romans 12, verse 12.
We see rejoicing and hope.
Patient and tribulation.
And then we see the commandment here continuing instant in prayer.
The title this morning is very simple, the right kind of persistence.
The right kind of persistence.
Let's pray, Father, I thank you, Lord, for this day.
God, I thank you for those that are gathered here, God, what a wonderful time to be in your house.
What a wonderful morning you've given us together.
So God, I pray, Lord, that we steward this well.
God, I pray you use me as a vessel for honorable use.
God, I pray that those that may be sick and at home, but
those that are traveling and listening online, God, I pray, Lord, that we are in
one spirit, one mind, in unity in Christ, God.
And we thank you for that.
So those that have ears to hear, may they hear?
And it's in Jesus' name, pray.
Anybody said?
Amen.
Like we have done with all the other commands thus far,
we're going to look at what it means to be continuing.
That phrase continuing instant in prayer.
If you have a different translation than the KJV, you might see the word devoted.
For example, the NASB 95 says, rejoicing in
hope, persevering in tribulation, devoted to prayer.
If you do not take your time and really study God's word, you might allow
our English language to dumb down truth
that is meant to be much deeper in the original language
that it was written in.
So for example, we see 2 phrases that can
be translated devoted right here in Romans 12,
but in 2 very different ways and meanings of the word.
We saw in Romans 12 verse 10 that we are told to
be kindly affection to one another.
That word, kindly affection, literally means to be devoted
to one another.
Now, this has to do with how we love each other, right?
We are to be devoted to each other in love.
By the way, listen, you've got you are commanded to love me.
You understand what I'm saying?
You don't have to light me.
You don't have to, you don't have to agree with everything with me?
But you're commanded to love me.
Guess what?
It goes both ways.
I'm commanded to love you.
As a matter of fact, 1st John, it talks a whole lot about this.
If you don't love your brother, how can the love of God be in you?
How can light be in you if you don't love your brethren?
In other words, if you say that you're walking with Jesus, but
yet you don't love your brothers and sisters in Christ, the Bible says
you're basically walking in darkness.
There's no truth in you.
Do you understand what I'm saying here?
It's very important to be devoted to each other in love.
That means that we take ourselves out of the equation sometimes,
and we live our life sacrificially serving each other.
But then you have in Romans 12, verse 12, the phrase continuing instant in prayer.
Now, what does this phrase mean in the Greek?
It means to persist.
To keep on with devotion.
What does it mean to be persistent?
If we're honest, all of us know and apply persistence
in certain areas of our life.
We are persistent in something in our life.
Every single one of us.
We got any TV people in the room.
Anyone like to watch TV?
Y'all a bunch of lying?
Listen, I like TV.
I enjoy watching TV, right?
I mean, you know, you can be more spiritual than I, whatever, okay?
But listen, we sit here and say, well, you know what,
I don't have time and I, but we're persistent.
anyone got our favorite TV show?
Yeah?
Okay.
Let's say you got a TV show of 10 seasons of 15 episodes
each at 45 minutes per episode.
Pretty common.
Amen?
Yeah.
Now, I'm gonna hurt the feelings of all of us.
I'm putting myself in there, TV watchers.
To get through that show, you have to spend
37.5 hours watching that show.
Look at look at the spiritual people in the room.
God forbid.
Oh, man.
Now, again, I'm standing up here, not self-righteously.
I have watched many, many TV series all the way through.
As a matter of fact, I've watched Little House on the Prairie literally 4 times all
the way through from season one, episode one, all the way to the end.
I had the DVD box set and it's in their little house that
they have and they built in Walnut Grove.
Like I am, I enjoy TV.
As a matter of fact, we last night we were laying
down before we were going to bed and Heather goes, you know that new little house on the
prairie is on Netflix.
And I was like, I can't do it.
I'm a purist.
Like that's not, that's not something I'm going to do.
And so we ended up watching it because, you know, I love
me in some little house in the Prairie.
And so he watched it and the entire time I was like, no, Charles would never have done that.
And why is that?
Caroline would have never said that.
And why is Mary not blind?
Like, I'm just sitting, like, just throwing it all, you know, he's
saying half pint, but this girl don't give me half pint vibes.
I mean, it's just like, and I'm just sitting there, by the way, I can't do it.
I'm going to try to do it.
give it another chance.
But listen, we all understand what we're talking about.
But to get through something like that, it takes persistence.
Now, I know that's really practical and that's really, you know, simple,
but we understand persistence.
How about those who have presently or who have her presently do sports, right?
Practice after practice, film session after
film session, coach lecture after coach lecture,
there's no telling how many hours are spent on
what we would call a game.
Why?
Because we know, and the world has told us, right?
And by the way, the world gets that truth that you have to be
persistent, if you're going to be successful, they get that from scripture.
They just don't attribute it to scripture.
But see, the world's told us that if you don't stay with it,
you're never going to be successful with it.
So what do you do?
You got to wrap your entire life around that thing.
Don't even get me started about golfers, right?
Anyone play golf up in here?
Yeah?
Listen, I play golf with Billy and Mark.
How long ago was that?
About 8 months ago or so?
It was, you know, never again, amen?
That was terrible.
I mean, that was just 1st off, this dude hits the ball really far, okay?
And when you don't hit the bar really far and the person that you're playing with
his ball really far, it's not fun.
Amen.
You just, you're sitting there.
I mean, I took so many more swings than that guy.
I was tired by whole 3 and it was just ridiculous.
But either way, think about it.
If you know anything about golf, you know that you can play golf every week,
multiple times a week for your whole life and still stink.
But it's no secret, it takes persistence.
This goes in every area of our life.
Potty training a child.
Raising a teenager.
Maintaining a career.
Staying in shape.
You've heard me say this in many variations, but the truth still stands.
You are persistent in what you care most about.
You are persistent.
in what you care most about.
What happens when you no longer care as much about that sport or
that job or that TV show.
Let's just keep with the illustration here.
You start calling out all the time for whatever reason.
You stop playing and practicing your craft.
That TV show goes into the keep watching category on Netflix and never leaves.
There's another truth in this.
Not only are you persistent in what you care most about, But
you are persistent in what you believe brings value to your life.
You will commit yourself to things that
you believe brings value to you.
What you keep doing is what you believe works.
I can tell you today with full confidence.
There's nothing in this life worth more than a faithful walk with Jesus.
The Bible all throughout urges us to stay devoted to the task at hand.
Stay focused on our purpose.
God has given us to not lose motivation in
the things of God.
In other words, we are told to continue.
If you've been in southern churches long enough, you'll hear the phrase to
keep on keeping on.
So what does the Bible have to say about persistence then?
Well, Paul, the man who was no doubt exhausted throughout his
entire life in ministry,
The man who we know went without so others could receive.
And, I mean, he literally, we talk about a scripture.
Philippians 4.13, for with Christ, all things are apostle.
He strengthens me.
You know, we talk about how, hey, you know, that means to kick a field goal or this or that.
No, what that means is whether I have or whether I have not, I can still
get through it because I have Jesus.
And so that's what this guy's talking about.
But one of my favorite scriptures in all the Bible, Galatians chapter 6,
verse 9 says, and let us not grow weary while doing good.
If we're in due season, we shall reap if we do not lose heart.
Let me ask you something.
Are you tired?
Are you weary?
See, oftentimes people see this as speaking about physical exhaustion.
And listen, we all get tired physically, but in reality, this
term weary speaks on spiritual exhaustion.
See, in the Greek, that word means that phrase means
become discouraged.
To give up.
To lose heart.
Physical weariness is one thing, but emotional exhaustion is a whole other beast.
Amen?
How often do we get discouraged and disappointed or
even doubtful that we are doing what we're doing is even making an impact?
There's things in life as we walk with the Lord that it
just hits this differently and this person disappoints us.
So that person leaves or, well, this person doesn't want to get all plugged
in and that person, you know, he's in and out, she's
the, this, and that, and you start to get discouraged.
is what I'm doing.
Is it even worth it?
Israel's history is full of ups and downs.
I do want to say this because I feel like the younger generation and not
just the younger generation, but a lot of the younger generation
is in this in this weird,
uh, you know, limbo of Israel.
And what are we supposed to do with Israel and all the things.
Go back to our media player that we have.
And I preached very clearly Romans 9 through 11 for
about 2.5 years and you can, you know, get all
you want for about Israel, okay?
But I want you to know something.
If you think the modern state of Israel is wicked.
Now, make sure to read your Old Testament.
Do you understand what I'm saying?
We get so caught up in recency
biased that we think that the wickedness that is going on today
just somehow developed in the half century.
That's not the case.
Church, there has been corruption and vile people on this earth since the beginning.
Don't you remember that the 1st child that was born,
he was a murderer, Cain, killed, Abel.
Why?
Out of anger and jealousy.
That's wicked.
Not to mention his parents, the 1st humans created.
Adam and Eve, they brought sin into the world.
We've been messed up for a long time.
Amen?
If you take the challenge to read the Old Testament, you will find that,
Israel, at some point they asked for a king.
They know they wanted a king like the other nations around them.
What they basically were saying is we want to be like the
pagan, heathen, idolatrous nations around us.
We want someone that we can see.
We want someone that we can that we can bow down to.
We want someone that can sit on the throne when they really had
that the entire time, Jehovah God.
Amen?
And I don't know if they just forgot, but you're talking about seeing something.
He literally led them to the wilderness with a pillar of clouds and a pillar of fire.
He literally sent manna.
He literally sent me.
I mean, like, like, they could see them, but it got to the point to
where they started to get callous thing.
looked around and they got jealous of whatever everyone else had.
So they asked for a king.
The prophet and time he warned them.
He said, hey, listen, you get a king, he's going to take, he's going to take all the things from you.
He's going to be corrupt.
He's going to be vies and be wicked.
Don, do it.
You have a king.
His name is God.
His name is Jesus.
Well, they asked for a king.
And God gave him a king.
So we see that we get King Saul.
But exactly what God said would happen, happened.
And King Saul became impatient and corrupt.
And he started doing things his own way.
Again, I'm paraphrasing a really big chunk of the Bible here, okay?
So just bear with me.
Before you know it, King Saul, he gets
he falls from favor of God and God
anoints David, right out of the shepherd
field, out of the sheep field, and Saul
finds out and doesn't necessarily find out, but sees
that, man, people are jealous or people like him better than him,
so he gets all jealous and he tries to kill David, he seeks
David's life, and so long story short, David eventually
becomes king, and David was a great king, but
because of the sin that he had and in his life,
God punished his family.
And this brought a consistent pattern of turmoil to the nation.
Now, understand, I know that was a whole lot.
What I'm trying to say is they got a king and then things got ugly.
Now, what does that look like?
If you read scripture, you're going to have many evil
kings for Israel and Judah to come and go.
All throughout script, you're going to see there was kings that did
evil on the side of God, then all of a sudden there was one king that
did good in the side of God, but to the one good king there might have
been 4 or 5 evil kings.
This has been going on for a long time.
Now, why am I even saying this?
And what does this have to do with Romans 12?
Well, one of those good kings was named Asa.
He was king of Judah.
As a matter of fact, Asa was a direct descendant of
David and the 3rd king of Judah.
His father, King Abijah, only ruled
for 3 years, but in that short time, just in 3 short
years, literally, he did wicked things throughout
his entire 3 years.
He did much evil in the side of God.
As's grandfather, Rehoboam, also did much
evil in the sight of God.
So when Asa became king, he had a decision to make.
Following the footsteps of his father and grandfather or do what is right.
Now we learn that King Asa decided to go a different way than his
predecessors and do what is right.
So we see this in 1st Kings 15, verse 10, and Asa
did that which was good and right in the eyes of the Lord his God.
Now, what does this consist of?
What did he do that was so right that everyone else didn't do?
Well, he his king, as
king, he began to reign with clear and precise reforms.
He was like, we're going to change things here.
He removed the male shrine prostitutes.
He cut down the Asheropoles.
By the way, these astropoles were sacred trees to
honor the Canaanite goddess Astra.
He was so committed to God's people, and getting
them back on track to the Lord, that
he removed his wicked grandmother from
her position as queen because she was an idol worshiper.
Because you imagine being so devoted, you go to your grandma's house, say get out.
I mean, this is how devoted he was.
Second Chronicles 14, one through four.
So Abba just slept with his fathers and they buried him in the city
of David and his son Asa became king in his place.
The land was undisturbed for 10 years during his days.
As said, they good and right, and started the Lord as God, for
he removed the foreign altars in high places, tore down the
sacred pillars, cut down the ashram, and commanded Judah
to seek the Lord God of their fathers, and to observe the law and
the commandment.
Now, I want to say this real quick and match this up.
There's a thing going on about having
the Constitution and the Ten Commandments in the schools.
Anyone know what I'm talking about?
And people are all just, I mean, they're just going, they're going crazy about this.
You got the camp that says, that's awesome, that's great,
which, I mean, no, duh, amen, praise the Lord, right?
Then you got the camp, that's like, oh, that's, well, you wouldn't want,
you know, the the Quran or this or that, and that's exactly right.
Why?
Because the Quran's not the word of God.
You know, the book of Mormon is not the word of God.
All right?
The new live in translation that the Jehovah Witnesses use is not
the book, is not the word of God.
So we're comparing apples and oranges here.
But notice that ASAP, he didn't give an
option to Judah.
He commanded them.
Look what it says.
He commanded Judah to seek the Lord God.
You do realize that today, people say,
well, we don't want to put parameters on things, and that's not as inclusive.
Let me just tell you something.
Look at the Ten Commandments.
God gave those for us to be protected.
In other words, that's exactly what we need.
It protects our relationship with God, and it protects our relationship with others.
All I'm trying to say is this.
I think it's a good thing if we sat back and said, you know what?
We ought to be commanded to seek the Lord God.
We're commanding to seek everything else.
So we see Asa here was doing his thing, man.
I mean, he was he was killing it.
And he was king for 41 years.
According to 2nd Chronicles 1612.
And Asa slept with his fathers and died in the one and 40th year of his reign.
Now, here's where it gets pretty good.
So I need you to lean in.
Asa had much success in bringing Judah back to the Lord.
He became king at 20 years old.
He was following 2 evil kings.
One being his father, the other being his grandfather.
And he boldly led in a god honoring way.
He wasn't perfect.
If you read about his story, he messed up pretty big time.
There was times where he should have repented of not trusting the Lord,
but instead he got angry.
There was times to where he had a disease in his foot.
This is actually what took his took his life at the end of his life.
And instead of going to the Lord.
He, he, he, he, depended on everybody else.
What I'm trying to say is, listen, his life was defined
by obedience to God, although he had some falls along the way.
That doesn't make the falls good, by the way.
Listen, we want to stay close to the Lord.
Amen?
Now, one Kings 15, 14.
15, verse 13 and 14 says this.
And also Mantra, his mother, even her, he removed
from being queen, because she had made an idol in a grove,
and Asa destroyed her idol and burned it by the Kedron.
So we see that.
But then we see, but the high places were not removed.
So we did a whole bunch, but there was some things that he wasn't able to do
or he didn't put enough time to...
But then look, we would say, well, you failed.
Hey, so you did all this good stuff for no reason, but look what it says.
Nevertheless, Asa's heart was perfect
with the Lord all his days.
Now, I already told you, he's made some mistakes.
Yet his life was defined by persistent pursuit
of God in his will.
Now, I do want to say this too.
Because we're seeing a times where a lot of influential believers
are falling and messing up and sinning.
And we should never tolerate or justify evil.
Amen?
But what we see here with King Asa was, he might have messed up.
He might have lost focus.
But his heart was always with the Lord.
It's kind of like his descendant David, a man
after God's own heart, although David sinned
in such a great way.
But do you want to know a turning point in his life?
Think about this.
How does somebody at 20 years old and all they know is evil?
I mean, you know he had to be influenced by his dad.
You know that he had to be influenced by his grandpa.
By the way, this gives this gives reason for us to listen.
We talk about this generational curse
on families, and I'm not saying that's not real.
We can have a doctrinal or theological discussion on that, but can I tell you something?
It ain't greater than Jesus.
I need you to realize something just because your daddy did it
just because your mama did it just because your grandma, granddaddy did it just
because your family's done it for generations.
does not mean you have to continue in that pattern of sin.
Listen, call upon the name of the Lord.
He comes in, he changes you.
That pattern, that curse is broken.
That's what the blood of Jesus does.
Amen?
Listen, I've got patterns of sin in my family going back.
Guess what?
My children will never know about it.
Why?
Because my parents said not with us.
Listen, that's how you do it.
So Asa, 20 years old.
Seeing all the influence he had, seeing the wickedness with
the people of God, he made a decision not under my watch.
So he started making reforms.
But it was a turning point in his life.
This is all going to hopefully come together, right?
Because right now you're thinking, man, you're all over the place, and that's okay.
God's prophet at the time was named Azariah.
Seeing King Asa going down a different path than his father and
grandfather, Azariah had a word of God for him.
Word from God.
2 Chronicles 15, verse 7.
Now hear this.
is good right here, but you.
Does it matter who did what before?
But you.
Be strong and do not lose courage.
For there is reward for your work.
In other words, what he's saying is, young man.
Be persistent.
Be devoted to what God has put on your heart.
Now let that settle in for a moment.
Is that not a beautiful?
Beautiful moment.
how God's truth is so everlasting.
You say, what do you mean how God's truth is everlasting?
Between the reign of King Asa and the ministry
of the apostle Paul is around a 1000 years.
A 1000 years.
That's 10 centuries unless I, you know, math has changed.
Amen?
Is that 10th centuries?
Yes, 1000 years.
That's a long time.
I can't even wrap my mind around that.
Yet, a 1000 years later.
What does Paul write?
Galatians 6, verse 9, and let us not grow weary while doing good.
For in due season, we shall reap.
If we do not lose heart.
The same advice Azariah gave Asa.
Paul gives us.
Be persistent in the Lord.
Philippians 313 through 14, brethren, I do not
regard myself as having laid hold of it yet, but one thing I
do, forgetting what lies behind and reaching forward to what lies ahead.
I press on toward the goal for the prize of the upward
call of God in Christ Jesus.
James wrote about this in James 112.
Blessed is a man who perseveres under trial.
For once he has been approved, he will receive the crown of life,
which the Lord has promised to those who love him.
The author of Hebrews wrote this in Roman, in Hebrews
12, verse one and two.
Therefore, we also, since we are surrounded by so
great a cloud of witnesses, let us lay aside every weight and
the sin which so easily ensnares us and let us run with
endurance the race that is set before us.
How do you run a race?
You run forward.
You never run backwards to win the race.
You gotta go forward, looking unto Jesus, the
author and finisher of our faith, who for the joy that was set before
him, endured the cross, despising the shame, and
has sat down at the right hand or the throne of God.
Listen, we are called to be persistent.
Persistence is not easy.
People ask me all the time, they said, how you doing, man?
Where are you at now?
I say, see the Grove, they say, well, you were there before.
How are you still there?
Because God has me here.
I don't need any other reason.
And we've been through some stuff.
Amen.
I've been discouraged.
I've been I've been doubtful.
Hey, if you don't think that I've, if you don't think that I've been ready to
give up, then, then we haven't talked enough, because I'm
just telling you right now, it happens, it happens.
But God has called me to persistence.
through the ups and downs.
You know what I've learned?
As all as as people go.
God sends more people in.
As as need has had.
God continues to meet the need.
Listen, we're, some of you that have just gotten
here, 1st off, we're so glad that you're here.
But if you could have just been with us 10 years ago.
You would understand, man, God has been good.
Why?
He is rewarded.
Our work.
Y'all women say amen.
Now, you might say, what in the world?
We in Romans 12, how we in 1st Chronicles and all these places.
Some of y'all didn't even know 1st carnivals in your Bible.
You should be a shame of yourself.
There's 2 of them actually.
1st and second.
Romans 12, verse 12.
Look at it again.
Rejoicing in hope, patient and tribulation, continuing steadfastly in prayer.
God commands us to be persistent.
But there's a detail to this command.
Look at what we were to be persistent in.
It's very specific here.
Continuing steadfastly in Prayer.
This reveals a sobering truth, and I want you to really get this.
Our prayer life.
is the primary indicator of our persistence for the Lord.
If you look at any one in the Bible that
God used in a mighty way, They had
a persistent, powerful,
earnest, fervent prayer life.
There's a quote from an unknown source that says this, no man is greater than his prayer life.
The pastor who is not praying is playing.
The people who are not praying is straying.
It is prayer that brings us close to God, our time of communion with the
creator of the universe, an ongoing conversation.
It never has to end.
We were able to communicate with the omnipotent one.
Have you ever seen these mega churches and I've been to a few for
conferences and stuff and it's like people line up to talk to the pastor and
listen, that blesses my heart.
That's all cool.
That's all good.
But you know, you can just go ahead and talk to the king.
Now, listen, I'm cool to talk with you.
I'm cool.
And we can meet, we can talk.
And if you want to take me to lunch, so be it.
bless you.
Amen.
But either way,
All I'm trying to say is, listen, I'm not the omnipotent one.
I'm not the creator of the universe.
Everything I try to create.
I mess up.
But see, what I'm trying to say is this.
Listen, it doesn't matter who he talked to on this earth, if we're
not talking to God, If we're not communicating with the Lord,
And we're straying.
We're just playing.
Church, if we are persistent, anything may be prayer.
There's no coincidence.
that what we talk about most in church of being of the
utmost importance, which is prayer.
Every church will say it.
is what the church does the least.
We have a Wednesday night prayer meeting.
You know why?
I started teaching again on Wednesday night?
Look, I'm not trying to get in anyone's irritated side.
Because people knew it was a prayer meeting.
And so they stopped coming.
because it's just a prayer meeting.
So to get them to come back, I started teaching.
Listen, hey, I don't have no problem teaching.
You want a lesson?
I'll give you a lesson.
Amen, what I'm saying?
Like, that's just what God has called me to do.
But what I'm trying to say is that's the perspective we have on prayer.
If I'd have stopped this service,
And I said, Mike and Robin, Joe, get back up here.
I sought the Lord, and he answered, listen, if
I just say, you know what, we're going to seek the Lord right now.
You know what happened?
People say, man, we're kind of, this is kind of a waste of time.
You'd have a few that come down, get broken before the Lord, but for the most part, you'd
be thinking, man, how many times are they going to sing this?
You don't think the enemy's done a good job of getting us distracted?
We're commanded to be persistent in prayer.
Commanded.
Unfortunately, many churches and many believers that turned prayer into a trivial ritual of corporate worship.
We put our prayer request on a sheet of paper and hope people read it.
We take 5 minutes of an hour and a half service and call out to the Father and we
wonder why we don't see anything we pray for yet.
We have lost or even worse, we have never had that persistence.
You know what's a beautiful reminder is when you pray for something over and
over again, and then all of a sudden you see God answer that prayer.
That church, our church has seen that here recently.
When Miss Jenny.
Is that not right, brother Bill?
Listen, hey, we prayed.
She was struggling with cancer, prayed, prayed, prayed, she had all these things going
on, all these scans.
It got every time we talked, it was getting scarier and scary.
It was.
I didn't even know how to, I got to the point where I didn't know how to encourage.
And then I got another phone call.
Why?
Because we've been persistent and God is good.
Hey, I just had the scan and has no cancer.
Persistence.
God will never command us to do something that will hurt us.
He commands us to do things that will help us.
Y'all with me this morning.
We're almost done.
Church, so far, this has been the most convicting command in Romans 12 for me.
Charles Spurgeon put it like this, as well, could you
expect a plant to grow without air and water, as to
expect your heart to grow without prayer and faith.
Adrian Rogers said this regarding the act of prayer.
prayer is not just getting ready for Christian service.
Prayer is Christian service.
Well, preacher, I just have a hard time making time for
persistent prayer.
I just, the day goes by so quickly and I
just, you know, you're a preacher, so you have time to pray.
So I get that, but like, I don't know how I can do this in my regular life.
Adrian also said Satan can't keep God from answering our prayers,
but he can keep us from asking.
We see the importance of prayer in the whole armor of God.
After explaining each part of the armor, look at what the admonition is.
Paul literally says, put on the whole armor of God.
Here's each piece.
And then he says in verse 18, praying always with
all prayer and supplication in the Spirit, being watchful
to this end with all perseverance and supplication for all the saints.
In other words, the finisher of the whole armor of God is prayer.
Continuing steadfastly in prayer.
I want to point one more thing about this word prayer in Romans 12.
It is primarily meaning the action of prayer and petition to the Lord.
In other words, what we see as prayer, talking to God.
However, in 2 instances, found in Acts.
speaks more specifically.
about a particular place of prayer.
Now, if you've already leaned back from when I said lean in, lean back in.
The church has put so many complications on
the idea of an altar.
God hit me with this when I was when I was reading this
and see, altors have been designated a designated
place of prayer and worship since the Old Testament times.
You would see, you would see people of God.
They would build an altar and they call upon the name of the Lord.
That's what they would do.
Doesn't mean they didn't call upon the name of the Lord before and after,
but they had a designated place, a designated time,
and they called upon the Lord.
See, you got some churches that use the altar to make a show and create
a sense of emotionalism and spiritual manipulation.
Then you have those who have an inch of dust on each altar step.
Guys, if we could be a church that just hits the middle ground on these things,
There's a way to balance that.
This altar that you see right here, you say, that's just steps.
And listen, we do.
We step up to get on stage.
When I came to the pulpit, I used these steps.
I didn't just jump or fly up here.
I understand they have a practical function.
But this altar right here, whether you like
it or not, whether you believe it or not, whether you know it or not, if you don't know it, you're going to learn.
This is for our local church.
This is a designated place of prayer.
I can look and think back on the altar.
Right here.
Listen to me, right here is where
I led my wife to Christ.
Right here.
All over this altar is where I've prayed for my brothers
and sisters in Christ.
I've seen, I've seen people repent.
I've seen people give their life to Christ.
I've seen people be restored.
We've seen people healed.
There's been a designated place of prayer.
And the church that I grew up in, I can bring you to the place where
I got saved.
It was at the altar.
I could have got saved anywhere, but in that time, it was
a designated place of prayer.
And I went down and gave my life to Christ.
I can show you the exact place to where I finally said yes to the gospel ministry.
When you get married, there's a designated place to make that commitment.
What he call it?
the marriage altar.
You don't just stand in between the chairs
that people sit in.
Like, where's the groom and the bride?
Oh, they're they're in section four, you know, road three.
Like no, that doesn't happen.
You have a designated place.
So we understand this concept.
So I guess if you want to know my heart about it, I believe
we need to stop making this an intellectual exercise about the altar.
and try to excuse the way a time response and, Well,
I don't need that and I don't do that.
I didn't, I didn't, that's not my style and just understand that as
a church, we have a designated place.
And there's no power in these steps.
But I believe there's power in the name of Jesus.
And I also believe that God tells us to be humble.
And there's not more humbling for us than to get upon our knees before God.
What prayers have you given up on?
I'm not saying you never pray about it.
But have you lost your persistence?
How about your lost loved one?
That one that you know, they died right now, hear me, church.
Don't, That one person that you
love so much that you know.
whether it be a spouse,
Whether it be a child, Mom, dad, whoever.
You know, they died right now, they go to hell.
And you've lost your persistence.
You've gotten used to that reality.
I believe that's what the devil wants us to be is used to
the reality, that people just dine and going to hell, what we have to do with it.
We know the one who can save them.
How about the healing you desire for yourself or someone you know?
It's so easy for us as a church when we're well,
when we're not sick to look at someone and think,
oh, it's such a pitiful situation, and I feel so bad, then
we go home, we don't think of it.
Where's our persistence?
How about that financial needs you have?
Instead of going to God in prayer, I'm not saying stop working.
I'm not saying stop grinding, but I'm saying, don't stop going to the Lord about it.
He owns a cat on a 1000 hills.
You understand what I'm saying?
He can provide and abundantly do so.
How about your marriage that is in shambles and
you sit there and you say, I've just, I've prayed and I've prayed
and nothing's ever going to happen.
Nothing's ever going to change.
It's just my life now.
Well, that goes against God's word because he says he wants you to have life and life abundant.
His will is not for that marriage to look like that.
As a matter of fact, his will.
We are called the bride of Christ.
We see what marriage should look like.
That's his will.
How about the guidance that you seek?
How about the revival that we all ask for in a church?
God send revival, send revival, twice a year.
We pray for revival.
Church may be persistent.
And we keep on being devoted to prayer.
Corey Ten Boone, a Dutch Christian.
You might have heard of her.
She saved 100s of Jews from the Holocaust.
Risked her life to do so.
She eventually was arrested and thrown in a concentration camp herself.
A situation if you've studied is unfathomable.
By the way, I want you to know, there are those that, that,
I believe another one of the enemy schemes to erase history.
They say, oh, well, the Holocaust never happened.
Listen, don't ever allow someone to erase such evil.
We need to understand, remember, and we need to realize
what happened.
But she said this about prayer, and it's so practical.
Someone, I think she was died 98 years old and
passed away, but she had such a practical advice.
She said, is prayer your steering wheel?
Or your spare tire?
We don't think about a spare tyrant until we need it.
God forbid we don't think about Jesus till we need him.
C.S. Lewis said this.
Prayer doesn't change God.
He's unchangeable.
But it does change me.
If your prayer life has not resulted in you being changed.
Could it be that you have not been persistent in prayer?
So heads back and eyes closed all over this place.